All right, welcome back uh to the second
AMR roundtable on uh overtures
discussion for the PCA general assembly
in 2026 in Louisville, Kentucky. Um we
are uh there's part one to this. So if
you missed that, you want to uh go find
a link on the AMR uh channel and uh and
watch that. But we're going to talk in
this segment uh about uh deacons, about
titles, ordination officers, and then
some of the other various um
miscellaneous overtures that have been
sent up. So to get us started, we're
going to uh we're going to talk about
overture 37,
which proposes allowing women to be
ordained as deacons. So I don't I I
don't remember what everyone said about
this one. I'm I'm sure not everyone is
for this one. Um, in fact, I might let
Steve go first on this and uh I know he
opposes this. So, let's go let's start
with opposition to Overture 37.
>> Yeah. So, I I think what I want to say
more broadly about all of these and I
think this is a good sort of segue into
that. A couple of things. Um
our our polity was more than sufficient
for 50 years at least uh to demonstrate
that we are a denomination that believes
that God only calls men to the office of
deacon. Um nothing has changed in our
polity. we've always had that position
from the beginning and arguably you
could say even before that but but
certainly since the you know the the
beginning of the PCA and so um obviously
there have been some things that have
been happening over the last couple of
years whether there have been things
that have been brought to light or
however you want to describe that that
suggest that there are those in the PCA
that have different opinions certainly
also those who have different practices
perhaps
um I I I I'm opposed to this overture
because I I I think it it contradicts
everything I believe about the office of
deacon. Uh that it is not open to women
that that that it is God who ordains or
who calls gifts and equipss the church
with their deacons and he does that
through uh qualified men. And so to have
such a radical change I think is um is
is certainly contrary to our
understanding of what scripture teaches.
It's been contrary to our historical
polity. Um but I also part of this whole
situation to me is that
on the one hand this is posed as a
discussion about the role of women in
ministry. Uh for me this is a theology
proper question before it's an
ecclesiological question. Um because
really what we're asking is but sort of
two different opinions. One that says
God again God only uh calls gifts and
equips men to an office and the other
that says that God calls equips and
calls gifts and equips men and women. Um
that's not really a statement about
women.
That's a statement about God.
And God either does or does not. And and
if you're going to say he does,
then every church that doesn't have
women deacons is sinning against God.
And if you're going to say that that God
only calls gifts and equips men, then we
can't install a woman into that office.
Uh, I also think to suggest in some way
that God does or does not call a woman
to the office of deacon depends in any
way on the vote of a session or of a
congregation.
Is again a confusion about our
understanding of God and his
relationship to the church. So I I I
think
there are some that I want to refer back
because I just want to say this is
really we don't need this. It's not it's
not helpful. This is one that I want us
to unanimously if possible say no to. I
I realize obviously it came from a
presbyterary so there's going to be a
handful of people who will vote yes
perhaps. Um, but I think even better
than some of the other overures, perhaps
the best statement the assembly could
make is is an overwhelming no, this is
not who we are as a denomination. It's
not who we've been um, etc. So, that's
sort of my I would say quick but
probably too late for that uh, view on
that issue and that overture in
particular.
>> Yeah, great. David,
>> the only thing I I agree with that and
the only thing I would add is that uh I
think even people in favor of women
deacons ought to vote no on this
question. The the makers have a burden
to offer persuasive material that would
lead a person to think that God wants us
to go in this direction from the
scripture. It has almost no scriptural
argument at all.
The the arguments are lists of scholars,
historical persons, and historical
practices and churches where women are
ordained. And I could just as easily,
anybody could just as easily give a list
of scholars, uh, historical leaders and
churches that think that's wrong. this
this overture does not deserve to pass
because it doesn't come close to uh the
burden that ought to be on an overture.
>> Howie, do you have anything to add to
this?
>> Always. Yeah. Um
I'm not in favor of any of the 10
overures that I consider in this
category.
Um,
I uh am fully convinced none of those 10
can get 58 presbyaries in favor. I know
that's a utilitarian argument or a
pragmatic argument, but why waste
everybody's time? As I said earlier or
maybe in the prior
taping,
um if you want something like this to
pass, develop consensus outside of the
assembly by persuading your brothers and
if it takes 5 years to do that, go
ahead. Um
um to the question of and I think maybe
some of these overures are trying to get
to this. Does God call, gift, and equip
men and women for service? Well, in one
sense, yes. not for office, but for
service. My wife has done more mercy
ministry than any human being in any
church I've ever been in. She doesn't
care what you call her.
Um,
but what I'd like to see is a little bit
of in the PCI toning down on the idea
that if someone is in favor of ordaining
women as deacons, which I'm not, it's
some it's somehow heretical when the ARP
and the RPCNA are
members in good standing in Napark and
they ordain women deacons. So, I think
we need to turn down the heat a little
bit, but no, I'm not in favor of this
overture.
>> I I'm going to avoid jumping in too
much, but I will say one of the problems
with the overure 37 that's been raised
is that it doesn't actually specify that
it's the session that determines this.
And so, it actually could be read that
churches now, all churches would have to
ordain women. And even though the
intention of the author was to make it
so that the session would decide that,
it wasn't clear I I believe in the
overure itself. And so I think the
author of that even was going to have to
bring an amendment to overures committee
uh as well. So there's some challenges
there. Um we'll talk about overture 72,
but I want to leapfrog because it's kind
of related to this. Overture 74 does
something different, which is it's
calling for a new chapter um that allows
explicitly for commissioning
non-ordained people. Um, and so I wanted
to hear if anybody had any thoughts on
that. That that's not the same, but
obviously it's relevant to this issue or
how do you all feel about that one?
>> Howie says send it back.
>> David, you what do you think?
>> I I would actually like to have it
referred to a study committee.
And uh given the things I say about
study committees, I need to call and
rescue my reputation.
Um I think study committees are good but
only in limited circumstances and I
think this is one of the limited
circumstances. It's where the church
knows that it has a question that is
presently necessary to solve for the
church's functioning.
>> Okay.
>> And and if they know what the issues are
and they say this is what we want to
hear about and any recommendation with
respect to how we can change or not
change. I think that's what study
committees are for and I've served on a
number of them that were in of that
character. I think that this overture
uh quite thoughtfully
raised questions that are broader than
the diacinate question having to do with
the possibility of commissioning of
non-ordained people. I've been in
churches that have done commissionings
of all kinds for all kinds of things and
I I've never been confused as to whether
that meant these people were deacons or
elders or ministers. But so to me there
there might be something to this. I'd
like to have a committee look at the
history of reformed especially American
Presbyterianism but other churches uh
and so look if there's any scripture
warrant I I for example I think the
commissioning of uh of uh
uh the people to go talk about the uh
Acts 15 council they weren't being
ordained
Uh even the commissioning of uh uh Paul
and Silas when they first went out, they
were both already ordained.
Uh there seems to be other sorts of
commissioning, but maybe I'm wrong on
that. But I'd like to see a very serious
study of scripture about that. I think
uh the history of our reformed usages
and that maybe there's something here
that would be helpful in the midst of
all of these discussions. So, I I I've
actually recommended that uh we send
this to a study committee and that
there's another overture I'd like to see
thrown into the mix and uh I think it
might be fruitful.
>> Okay. What's the other before I jump to
Steve? Um what's the other overture that
you wanted to send to us?
>> I was afraid you were going to ask me
that.
>> Okay. Well, you think about it and
Steve, let's jump over to you. What what
do you think about the 74 about
commissioning not people in non-ordained
ministry?
>> Yeah. Well, I think that
certainly this is something that has
happened in many churches throughout the
PCA. Um it it's happened, you know, the
need for a chapter or a subchapter in in
the BCO. U I think there's some
I think it could be helpful to a certain
degree in establishing boundaries and
guidelines. This is what it is. this is
what it's not. Uh
this isn't one of the ones that rises to
the top that I think is is that
important, so to speak. Um I'm
intrigued. Anytime David says, "Let's
send this to a study committee." Um I I
perk up because I I I've never heard
that before in my life. Um haven't been
the PC all that long, but I've never
heard that that phrase before from him.
Um, but uh I I just I I think it it it's
presented as a as a solution to a
problem that may or may not even exist,
so to speak. So, I mean, I think that's
one of the areas that's a little bit
confusing. Um, I was also turned off by
the the second whereas where it talks
about Paul and Barnabas being
commissioned prior to their later
appointment of elders in the churches. I
I'm not sure why those two sentences
were placed together. Um,
first of all, they were not appointed as
elders in the churches. They were
appointing elders in churches. So, those
two seem to be a nonsequiter. I didn't I
got stuck on that one. So, uh, but
beyond that, um, I I just I don't think
it rises to the level of, uh, needing
the change. Um, or at least with
everything else that's going on. Uh but
yeah, I'd love to hear more about a
study committee and how that might be
helpful for it.
>> Howie, do you have any thoughts on this?
>> Yes, I do. Um,
we had an SJC case years ago out of
Rocky Mountain Presbyter where the SJC
ruled that um,
as long as you
make it very clear that the person is
not being ordained.
Uh, in that particular case, you could
call them, you could use the word
minister generically.
Um
we will we have had and will always have
non-ordained church staff, non-ordained
church volunteers.
Um that it's good to sometimes set them
apart, honor them, recognize them. Um
but the idea that you would elect any of
those people to me is I think extremely
unwise and unnecessary.
Uh the idea that you would have them
kneel in the front of the church and
have land hands laid on them for prayer
like you would with ordination I think
is unhelpful and unwise.
Um whether you use the verb commission
or appoint or set apart or something
like that. Um if commission makes my
brothers really nervous, I'll find
another verb. Um
um so
I do think it's valid to find ways to
honor, recognize, set apart in front of
the church people that are
non-ordained volunteers and church
staff, but it can't look like
ordination.
>> Yeah. I mean, I will say that to your
point, Steve, about why is this needed?
I mean, I think this year there's been a
lot of things circulated about different
practices of different churches that a
lot of people are trying to say, well,
what what does this all mean? And I
think this is an attempt to clarify what
it could mean and what it shouldn't
mean. Um, so whether or not that's
needed is another question, but I think
that's the occasion in which this and
several of the other overures on this
topic came up. I mean there was a big
firestorm online about that and several
presbyteries have received 40-5
complaints against um against individual
sessions for various practices. So
David, were you going to say something
else? Uh 52 was the other um uh overture
and let me say I agree entirely with
Steve on his criticism about uh uh the
uh commissioning and then appointing of
elders. I don't know what those two
sentences had to do with each other. I
maybe they were asleep at the wheel or
uh but uh in any case overall
the the diiacinal issue has spilt over
into all kinds of wanting to make rules
about what language you could use and
what motions you might make or and I
think it's getting out of hand. Um
I am uh fully on board that well well I
I mean I'll make my confession. When I
was ordained as a ruling elder I took
exception to uh women not being allowed
in the theinate. I thought with from
Warfield's influence and from I mean I
almost thought Warfield couldn't be
wrong. And uh I uh also thought that
there was something to be said for the
Phoebe thing. And I had no idea how
women appear in the pastorals in the
middle of that discussion of the theol
office. But um and so I long held that.
Um uh but um later when I was challenged
more by it uh about it by a friend uh I
went back and looked again and uh I
think in fact our book of church order
is wrong when it says that the diiacinal
office is not one of rule but only of
sympathy and service. I think the diiaal
office is one of rule. It its rule not
like the elder with respect to the whole
church but its rule with respect to a
particular ministry.
The seven appointed in Acts were not
appointed to feed the widows. They were
appointed to make sure there was an
equitable distribution of the things
that went to the widows. That's a matter
of judgment and rule. And when you look
at at our description of what the
diiacinal office is, there's authority
attached to at least half of the things
that it says deacons should be doing.
A a a narrower kind of rule with respect
to these things. And that's what changed
my mind. Uh I I came to believe that
what Paul says, I don't allow a woman to
have authority over a man with respect
to ecclesiastical things is perfectly in
fact consistent uh with what he has said
in other places and how we ought to
think about the that's what changed my
mind about women deacons
>> um but having said that I don't uh what
the
unusual zeal now people seem to have
about trying to crush the opposition on
this subject. I I like how he's turned
down the heat a little bit, but and but
and now it seems to me this year,
especially with a number of these
overures, to be spreading out to a kind
of uh
poison that if you say anything that
sounds anything remotely like uh trying
to identify some person as being useful
in the service, you know, I'll one more
thought and I'll shut up. the um the uh
you know New Hope we teach our folk that
the diiacinal ministry belongs to the
whole church.
Every member has a responsibility with
respect to caring for others and in fact
it's the members who are the first line
of diagonal ministry.
They're the ones who ought to be caring
for one another daily and and uh
evidencing the community of the saints
and that the act deacons are there when
the task is greater than what one or two
together on their own could do when it
needs organization when it needs um
leadership that that's what the deacons
are about. And so when you start talking
about like there'd be something wrong
with saying that non-ordained people
shouldn't take up these offices in some
way and we're saying all it is that is
helping other people. I I think we're
going to distort our um ministries. Um
so that's why I think it would be good
to have such a study committee
>> for you. 74 and 52 should go to a study
committee. Um And Steve, were you going
to follow up on David's comments there?
>> No. Okay. I thought you might I thought
you had something to add there. Okay. Um
others in this bucket, I don't want to
neglect overture 72,
>> which is uh requiring sessions to report
elders and deacons in their minutes. Um
did uh did anybody have any thoughts on
that? It looks like
you guys seem to all be in favor of this
or one of you said refer back.
>> Howie, I think you said refer back.
Yeah, I mean I've been around long
enough to be able to read between the
lines and this is basically to me a
fishing expedition to find out which
churches don't have diacinets.
If you want to do that, make a BCO
change that says you must have a
diacinet in which case you probably
should specify what the quorum is
because a church could have a diacinate.
There are churches with a diacinate of
one person, right?
So, if you want to pass a law that says
you must have a diacinate,
uh, and you don't specify that you must
have three,
um, I I see no other reason why overture
72 was filed. Thank you.
>> Well, I think there's two reasons. I I
get the the undercurrent um, you know,
whatever. So I I think pragmatically,
which is a word, how he loves, I I do
think there's a helpfulness to this and
even before we get to deacons to to know
from a presbyterary point of view where
churches stand in terms of the number of
elders that they have because there have
been certain circumstances in different
presbyteries where I we find out months
later that a church is down to one elder
or no elders. Uh so in one sense just
having a list and to know okay this is a
healthy church they've got a good number
of elders we we I know that's the not
the only metric for healthiness but I
think there's a there's a usefulness to
that. Um the other thing about the
deacons and and maybe this isn't the way
to get get around it or get to the
issue. Um but you know something David
had communicated earlier and I'll let
him talk more about it if he wants but
um I I think our our polity is again
clear enough that the only reason you
should not have a deacons or at least a
deacon is because you're willing to say
God has not gifted us a deacon. That
should be the only reason you don't have
a deacon.
Uh impossible should not mean it's
impossible for us to have deacons
because I want women to be deacons too
and so therefore we can't have any de
you know that that that's not I realize
that falls under the rubric of
impossible the way it's written now but
but if you take our polity as a whole
that cannot be what that means. Um and
so whether or not this is the right way
to get to it I don't know. Um but I
think that's a
A it has been a paradigm shift paradigm
shift in the PCA over whether it's been
over a decade or whatever where
uh the the notion of impossible to have
deacons has shifted from I think what it
originally intended to say uh to being
more of a a commentary on the office
itself. And if a church just like if a
church doesn't have enough elders church
has no deacons or even only one deacon
um they should be the ones fervently
praying to God that he would pour out
those gifts and the elders should be
doing everything they can to train up
men to take on that role. um you know
and I I I'll say one more thing you know
going back to you know acts and and sort
of the establishment of this office um
one of the things I tell my my group and
officer training is that as much as you
that that section in acts is about the
establishment of a diacinate it also
says as much about the office of elder
that these are important matters that
they hand to these men to deal with but
one of the main reasons why they hand
those matters to them is so that they
can focus on the ministry of the word
and prayer. And so if the the
responsibilities of the diacinate are
devolving to the session because it's
impossible for them, they have to do all
of those. And and so it is it that's how
it was so important that the elders
focus on the word and prayer and that
these very important uh mercy issues
were handled authoritatively. I agree
with David.
that that Christ gives the church
another office. So I I think it's it's a
it's a shift, a paradigm shift that
needs to go back the other way. And I
don't know how to do that. Maybe an
overture is the wrong way to do it, but
I think it needs there's some sort of
way we need to get to that in in our
denomination.
>> I just want at some point
I I think the deacon issue is far less
important than the elder issue. And I
think the PCA believes that we kicked
the CRC out of Napark
when they started ordaining women
elders. At that time, the RPCNA and the
ARP had ordained women deacons. We don't
treat it the same way. I want I want
someone to say
this diagonal issue is of paramount
importance and I think the ARP and the
RPCNA should be booted out of Napark.
That to me is consistent. If you're not
going to say that, I don't think that
you you're being consistent. I'm not
talking to anyone on this call. No, no,
no, no. But I'm just saying it doesn't
make sense to me otherwise. Well, if I
could just throw in um the um I I agree
uh with Howie's suspicion of overtures
like this. We've also had overtures like
this before where there was wanting to
have various kinds of reporting that
they were clearly looking for a way to
get evidence. the I don't think that's
what's going on in 73 or I mean 72
partly because uh I know Ascension
Presbyter
if is if this had come from another
presbyter I might be pretty confident of
its character but I doubt that from
Ascension and in the meantime I think
that Steve has mentioned uh some
important areas where this kind of
reporting would be valuable to have
regardless of what you think about our
current controversies and there are more
I think and uh uh so I think it'd be a
very good thing if uh we began to have
this kind of reporting.
>> Okay. Um somewhat related overture 61 uh
declare the Danver statement uh to be
biblically faithful. Um Howie, do you
want to start and make a few comments
about that?
>> Sure. I don't like declaring things. Um,
first of all, it's just what the
majority of 2,000 guys in one city did
in one year. Uh, it's not the PCA, it's
the guys that showed up in a majority at
that particular assembly. Um, secondly,
there's a lot of words in the Danver
statement and um, it could be more
biblically faithful if we tweaked it.
Um,
thirdly,
um, it's a 38-year-old document and it
isn't written as well as it could be. It
was at a particular cultural moment,
um, when radical feminism, I think, was
more threatening than it is now.
Um, I know that, uh, some of our own
scholars have critiqued Danver.
Um, I know that Piper and Grudom both
favor women deacons and they were
primary authors of Danver. So, I just
don't think it's a a wonderful uh
statement. I think it could be improved
and I don't understand why we are
um being asked to declare it as
biblically faithful. Is this supposedly
a alternative to the diagonal overtures
or something? I'm a little bit confused.
So,
>> okay. Anybody else have any thoughts on
that? It didn't look like any of y'all
supported that.
>> Well, I mean, I I would probably
in one level, I mean, I don't think this
is one that I would want to say no to.
These are the kind of overtures in a way
um regardless of the of the content that
that I don't like because
to say no to 61
will automatically go on, you know, out
into the Twitter verse as you know PCA
rejects Danver's uh statement and all
that it uh you know all that it says.
Um, and so in that sense, I I'm I'm
never really super happy about those
because you're you're sort of uh in
trouble if you do to modify a statement
and in trouble if you don't. Um, and so
in that sense, none of those really
excite me terribly much. Um I I do think
that some of the
the principles that are enumerated in it
are you know thought to be uh you know
the argument is is that you know these
are these are principles. Let's begin
with principles and then we can go to
the practical matters. Um and in in in
that sort of scheme I'm I'm 100% in
favor of that. I always want to start
with principles before I get to what we
do. Um, so in that sense, I don't have a
problem with the issue. I don't have a
problem with Danver statement. Uh, I
mean, how said it's 30 years old. Well,
it's echoing biblical language that's
2,000 years old. So, I mean, it's not
the age of it, it's whether or not it is
in fact biblically faithful. Um, so
maybe we can postpone it indefinitely or
something along those lines so we don't
actually have to do anything with it. Uh
because again, I don't I don't know that
it's going to I I don't think it would
have a problem passing the assembly. I
really don't. I mean, the Nashville
statement really didn't either. There
was a lot of debate and discussion over
it. Um and I don't think the assembly is
going to have a hard time declaring it
biblically faithful. Uh it's just a
question of
is that is that going to speak into the
issue that's really before us. I think
principally speaking, um, in so far as
the Damber statement is biblically
faithful, we all already affirm it
anyway.
So, in that sense, I I I understand the
need for it. I understand the point. Um,
I I'm I'm always opposed to statements
that if we say no to, it makes it sound
like we hate something when we just
didn't think it was, you know. So, all
of those things wrapped up together, I'm
not sure how to deal with it, but that's
kind of where I'm at.
>> Howie, what about you? Yeah, I think I
heard a previous speaker say something
about not knowing why it's needed. I
don't know why it's needed. That's my
point. When if I wrote an overture and
someone said, "Why is this needed? What
what is he trying to accomplish here?"
Um, but we don't have to answer it yes
or no. Um, we could uh refer it back to
Presbyter
assembly postpone consideration
indefinitely.
uh several years ago, I can't remember
the city, um there were competing
overtures to memorialize
one of our church leaders who had died,
I'll say. And one was a complimentarily
memorializing and one was not
complimentary. And so I took people out
to dinner. I said, "Listen, we can't
have this. Uh we need to postpone
consideration indefinitely of both of
your overtures because this can't work."
And that's what was done. And I think
this is what we need to do on this one,
too. So,
>> well, I I think we could uh deny the
overture and say uh we deny because it's
not our the part of our church's calling
to hear and endorse statements of other
part parts of the church or
institutions. We have enough to do to
care for our own house.
>> Okay.
>> I like that, too.
>> I'd like to shut this down.
>> No more Nashville. No more bands here.
>> Yeah. Yeah, we did that last year, too.
And Yeah. Um, okay. So, Westminster 31
uh is about elders distributing the
Lord's supper. Only elders. Um, all of
you said no to this one. I think uh it
seems like last year.
>> Well, no. Well, yes, but I think the
easy answer is
>> you got a directory of worship study
committee. It's in that it's in that
section of the book. hear what they have
to say and uh right if it's being
proposed for adoption which I think it
might be um send it down to get adopted
and then if it gets adopted then you can
make these proposals later to to tweak
it but yeah to do this precipitatively
um
>> yeah that idea
>> okay anything else related to deacons uh
officers ordination titling that you
wanted to take up I I don't think any of
you had identified any of the other ones
related to this as something that you
wanted to discuss. Okay. All right.
Well, then let's just jump to talk about
some of the miscellaneous overures to
kind of end this segment. Um there is
there are a couple I think three uh over
66 from Philadelphia, one from Calvary,
76, 89 from Fellowship that want to uh
give thanks for the 250th anniversary of
our nation's founding. Uh, do you all
have any thoughts on that one?
>> Yeah, I I I thought I think it's a great
idea. Uh, I realized that some of the
wording might be a little heavy to to
get past. I think one of them said
basically all of these whereas
statements we're adopting more or less
and and that's always a bad idea. Um but
we we certainly believe in in a God of
providence and a God who raises up
nations and casts them down for that
matter. And in God's kindness and
providence, he has, you know, kept our
nation uh whole and together for 250
years. Um there is not another nation on
earth or in history that I would rather
live in than the one that I live in now.
Um and I thank God for that. I thank God
for the freedoms that we have here in
this country. Um the freedom of religion
that we have and it's not a perfect
country. Um there's lots of things I'm
sure all four of us could list that we
would love to see changed. Uh but I
think uh thanking God for uh for that
for what we have is always a good thing.
And so I 250 is certainly a monumental
uh year. Uh I think it's a good thing.
the exact language might need to be
tweaked and changed and and you know
maybe saying less is better than saying
more. Um perhaps given the study
committee on Christian nationalism
there's an overtoned or an undertone
perhaps to all of this
>> but I don't I don't think there needs to
be. Um I I pray every Sunday for the
civil magistrate uh try without fail um
regardless of who's in office, state,
national, and local level because God
calls us to. I think giving thanks is a
good thing. So yeah, I'm in favor of the
idea if not necessarily the details.
>> Yeah. Howie.
>> Yeah, I'm very much in favor of giving
thanks. I mean, I spent eight years in
the Air Force. I'm pretty fond of
America. Uh, I think we can do that in
one I think we can do that in one
sentence. Uh, we don't have to
drag in anything else.
I was a little bit concerned about the
phrase countenance and maintained by the
civil magistrates. One of the
confessional differences I've expressed
to every session ever have been on. Uh,
I'm pretty sure I don't think that uh
the same way as they did in 1647.
Uh maybe the Americans understanding of
countenance and maintain civil
magistrates different than
uh it was in London way back then, but I
don't agree with what I understand them
to have believed. So I didn't want to
see that language in there. I think we
can adopt one sentence and genuinely be
thankful uh for God's providence in this
country. For sure.
>> David, do you have anything to add?
>> Well, I Yeah. Uh no, not really. I don't
I wish I wish it hadn't been as long as
this because it just opens up. But on
the other hand, I was expecting it to be
far more flag waving in an unh wholesome
sense than uh it is. I thought it was
pretty tame for
uh
but I agree with Howie that uh citing
the larger catechism in this context in
the way they site it
seems to me to be a mistake
and it it either ought to be stricken or
I mean the way I would have put it is
that uh
uh that the church may be b countenanced
and maintained by the civil magistrate
meaning countenance and it maintained as
any other institution of social
well-being. I think that's what the
Americans meant. It's the only thing
that's consistent with the uh um
amendments that were made in 1789 to the
confession of faith. I think they
decided not to change the shorter
catechism because this was a perfectly
fair reading of it and it would ought to
be read that way in the new context that
uh the amendments made. But I think we
need to draw attention to that. We can't
just especially in this context today,
>> right?
>> We can't.
>> Or it could have been that they were
like us and sometimes we change
something not realizing we should have
changed something else at the same time.
>> That could be that could be. Well, it
certainly is a complicated year for it
to be the 250th anniversary and for us
to be talking about establishment and
Christian nationalism and all that. So,
in a year when we need to move quickly,
it's kind of unfortunate that there's
these little potential hiccups on
something that I think everyone would
agree with, which is being thankful for
for God's kindness to our country. So,
all right. Well, let's talk about um the
one overure from last year that was
pushed forward, the 2025 overure 49 from
Pacific Northwest uh at interim study
committee on artificial intelligence. Um
Howie, do you want to speak to that
first?
>> Yeah, I was not at the presidentary
meeting where that was proposed, so I
wasn't um privy to the debate. Um I've
got two sons that work in AI. I don't
know what they're talking about when
they talk to each other. Um, I went to
see a documentary called The AI Doc and
the first half of it scared me to death
and the second half of it made me very
excited. So, um, it is a huge thing.
Um, they, uh, some of the people in AI
liken it to the discovery of fire and
how that will change the world. So,
um, I don't argue that it's not
important. I can't argue that it's not
important. Um,
but my sons also say that these AI
companies are leaprogging each other
every two weeks. Uh, so a study
committee report is going to be outdated
by the time it comes out. Um, but I'm
I'm not opposed to it for sure because
it is an hugely important topic. It
could be important to to the church as
well. Um,
>> okay.
>> Maybe that's what the study committee
>> Yeah. You sound a little indifferent.
You're not really sure yes or no on that
one.
>> Because I'm I'm not intelligent.
>> Okay.
>> Artificial or otherwise.
>> Yeah. Right. Steve, what do you think
about this? Do you think we should have
a study committee on artificial
intelligence?
>> Yeah, I I I think it could be very
helpful and a couple of reasons. I mean,
one,
obviously, if the study committee comes
back and says, you know, pastors and
students using AI to write their sermons
or their papers is bad, well, everybody
should already know that um already.
>> Um, I do think that there are some kind
of broader pastoral concerns
uh related to especially younger people
and their engagement of it. um in much
the same way that it might have been
helpful 10 years ago if if we had a
study committee on maybe social media
>> that that again not good or bad but
providing pastoral resources for people
to deal with the epidemic of that that
has infected our church and and you know
to the point where I don't even get on
Twitter anymore hardly ever get on
Facebook because of the nature of the
conversation that's obviously that's a
totally different discussion But, uh,
back to AI, um, I I think having some
wiser guys, and when I say wiser,
probably they will have a full head of
hair, and none of it will be gray, uh,
but they're wiser on these matters
because they they deal with it and, uh,
know some of the the the pits that that
we might fall into. They obviously can't
get them all. um but to provide some
resources and just even if it's just
awareness to the church more broadly
about the dangers that are involved in
this far outside of plagiarism uh I
think could be helpful. Um you know it
could also be so milk toast that we all
look at it and say well I could have
written that. Uh, but I've also found
while I I think I don't think I've ever
voted in favor of a single study
committee, uh, except maybe one or two,
but but beyond that, I'm always
pleasantly surprised at how well they
end up coming out. Uh, even ones that I
was like, "Oh, please, let's not do
this." By the time you get it and read
it, you're like, you know, actually,
this is really good. Uh, maybe not 100%,
but 95 is not bad, you know, for what
we're doing. So, I I think in that
sense, it could be helpful. So, um, it
all just depends on obviously who gets
on it, what their parameters are, but
but I think it could be helpful.
>> All right, David, last word on this one.
I think I I've had all the words that I
should offer on it. I'm just against
study committees unless they're for a
distinct purpose that needs to be
accomplished by the church and the
church needs to be guided by it. I think
that in general study, I'll put it this
way, the best resources for our folk are
not assembly study committees, but the
intellectual and spiritual wealth we
have in our ministers, teachers, and
scholars through academic institutions,
conferences, publications, broadcasts,
uh, recordings, journals, and magazines.
>> Okay. So you're also then opposed to the
other study committee which is overture
80 from Calvary on uh CT and CRT and you
said even with prejudice like that it
was out of order. So tell us more about
that.
Well, I just say that
one of the whereases
uh refers to um not by name but refers
to leaders in the PCA who hold the crit
critical race theory and it's footnoted
it's footnoted to the Vanguard Presbyter
website an article by Dwey Roberts who
names them and it's highly critical of.
Now, I think that violates Robert's
rules.
>> I don't think we can have a debate where
somebody in the debate makes allegations
about a brother in the PCA. And that's
what the wherees are. It's debate.
>> So, I'm thinking seriously about asking
at least that whereas to be ruled out of
order. But I mean, I I I take it you've
all had a chance to read it. They wrote
the study report they wanted already in
the warehouses.
That thing is a a laying out of
everything that they think is terrible
about critical race theory, most of
which I agree with. But I think it's an
abuse of of an overture. If it gets
voted down, they will have already
succeeded in what they wanted was to get
that message out because everybody in
the assembly should have read it.
>> Uh,
well,
>> all right, Howie, what do you think?
>> Yeah. No, I agree with David. I mean, if
someone has a position on something, uh,
don't make an overture to form a study
committee. Write the paper yourself. Um
I didn't we didn't ask in Pacific
Northwest for a study committee on
voting age restrictions for
um minor communicants. We wrote a 20page
rationale and attached it to the
overure.
Do it that way.
>> Steve, what do you think about this?
Well, um, unfortunately
I did not get an opportunity to read,
uh, Overture 80 given how how recent it
came out and its link. Um, so I I I
don't I can't speak intelligently to
that. I I I did see what David had
pointed out and in earlier
communications and when it saw what he
was talking about and I agree with what
he said. um like do I do I think that CT
and CRT are bad things and and shouldn't
be in the PCA or in the church broadly?
Yes. Uh again, I'm not so sure that a
study committee is going to fix that so
to speak. And at the end of the day,
it this is very different from the
Christian national uh study committees
where there were a number of
Presbyteries that were saying this is a
difficult issue. We're dealing with some
problems. Can you ple basically sort of
a Macedonian call, right? Can you
brothers help us out? We're not really
sure. We would love to get broader
wisdom on the PCA on this issue. Um,
I know that there were some who were
favorable of of some of the Christian
nationalism or at least some uh some
things that are in that orbit that
thought of it as uh all they're asking
for is the ammunition they need to go
file charges against people. Um, but
a study committee can't really be
introduced as evidence in a an
ecclesiastical trial anyway. If you
can't establish it from scripture in the
confession, then I mean the study
committee might add all it's gonna do is
add more more paper to the record of the
case that eventually has to get read by
the SJC. So I if someone thinks that
that CT or CRT is outside of the bounds
of the PCA then again uh back to what
David said a long time ago. Well, you go
and you talk to them and if you can't
come to an agreement, then there's
there's mechanisms for dealing with
issues that you think are contrary to
scripture. Uh so in that sense, I'm not
sure how important or necessary it is.
um much like Howie uh this was back when
I was in Ascension and uh echo uh
David's comments on the character of
that presbyter but um we were concerned
about um the book u still time to care I
think it is uh we we established a
presbyary level study committee that
read it and commented on it and was
distributed to our presbyter for there
were a number of churches that were
dealing with some issues that we thought
it would be helpful for them that
there's nothing that says this has to
come from the denomination
and and particularly when the whereases
which to be fair I have not read are
most of the five first five pages u it
seems as though they already done plenty
of research on whether or not this is
good or bad so from that perspective I'm
not u not terribly in favor of it um but
we'll we'll see we'll see how it goes
All right. Well, gentlemen,
>> I wanted to clarify. I wasn't impugning
Ascension Presbyter.
>> No, David was defending Ascension
Presbyter. That's all I was.
>> Every presbyterary clerk
should know who the ruling elders are.
And all he has to do is send an email to
the session clerk and say, "Hey, who are
your ruling elders?" the there's a
whereas clause in there that references
this was attempted last year via an RAO
change that RAOO change proposal failed
so we're going to try it by BCO and so
that's where my comments come from so
but no I was in essential material
>> that's back over 72 yeah sorry
>> okay well I think I think we've tackled
this uh these two buckets pretty well
and so I think we're going to wrap up
this uh second part So, thank you guys
for taking the time and uh for those
watching, we're going to have one more
part that deals um with judicial matters
and polity matters. So, we hope that
you'll tune in for that. Thanks.